Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Street Art Fair Records 1960-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Street Art Fair records 1960-2005, 1968-2005
Ann Arbor Street Art Fair (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
10 oversize volumes
2.8 linear feet (in 3 boxes)
Corporation administering the summer juried art fair in Ann Arbor, Michigan. The art fair is the oldest of three fairs that comprise the annual Ann Arbor art fairs. Minutes, bylaws, financials, and other materials relating to the administration of the art fair; also press materials, artists' evaluations, scrapbooks documenting development and history of the fair, and photographs and slides of the fair and the work of the artists.
0168 Bp 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 9086 ) was received from Shary Brown of the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair in May 2001.
The record group is open for research.
The Ann Arbor Street Art Fair is the oldest of the three fairs that make up the annual Ann Arbor Art Fairs. Held since its founding on South University, East University, and Church Street, it is also generally acknowledged as the most prestigious of the three fairs, garnering recognition as one of the nation's finest juried art fairs. The fair is a nonprofit organization. Types of work exhibited have included paintings, weaving, pottery, prints, photography, sculpture, and more.
The fair was originally planned in 1959 as a way to draw increased crowds and attention to the Summer Bargain Days. During Bargain Days, merchants ran sidewalk sales and other promotions to encourage downtown shopping. Actual institution of the Street Art Fair began during the 32nd annual Bargain Days in 1960, July 20-22. The objectives of the first fair were "to enable the public to meet, talk with and buy from professional artists" and "to provide an interchange of ideas and techniques."
One of the founders and early committee leaders was Esther Rainville. She was instrumental in establishing the long range vision and plans for a permanent, annual art fair of high caliber. Local organizations involved included the Ann Arbor Art Association (AAAA), the Chamber of Commerce, the South University Businessmen's Association, and the University of Michigan. Other local artists' groups, such as the Handweavers Guild and the Potters Guild, also cooperated by exhibiting their work there. In all, over one hundred local artists sold their work or gave demonstrations at the first fair. Because of the fair's success in its first year, organizers decided to make it an annual fair.
Compared with later fairs, the first art fair was small, including only three tents and the rest of the items hung from wires strung between parking meters. Though at first organizers had difficulty finding exhibitors, the fair quickly grew in size, quality, and the geographic diversity of its participants. In 1961 there were over 260 registrants and sales came to around $9,000. The fair continued to grow in both size and renown, with artists from as far away as Japan included among the over 400 participants in 1966. By 1968, the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair had established a national reputation for excellence, and sales topped $150,000.
Applications had originally been accepted on a first-come, first-served basis. However, as the fair grew, concerns grew about its size. Also raised were worries about maintaining a high level of quality. To this end, a jurying process was instituted in 1965, for the 1966 fair. This process, along with the influx of artists and artisans from across the nation, drew some criticism from those who felt that the fair had moved too far away from the original purpose of showcasing local talent.
In more recent years, important issues have been the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair Committee's relationship with the local merchants association and the establishment of closer working ties with the other two fairs, the Summer Art Fair and the State Street Art Fair. In the 1990s, the Three Fairs Committee was formed to investigate ways of increasing cooperation among the fairs.
Also in the 1990s, there was a renewed association with the merchants group (previously called the South University Businessmen's Association and since renamed the South University Merchants Association, or SUMA). Eventually, in late 1997, the primary body representing South University area merchants reorganized as the South University Area Association (SUAA), and contention between the AASAF Committee and SUAA escalated. Issues at stake were the sharing of fair revenues, the number of SUAA representatives who should serve as AASAF board members (with SUAA stipulating that two-thirds of the board must be chosen by SUAA), and ultimately, control of the art fair itself.
In 2001 some resolution was reached. The AASAF Committee agreed to a temporary revenue-sharing and payment plan with SUAA. AASAF also made plans to move, in 2003, to an as-yet unspecified location, at which point it would not be required to make payments to any other entities other than the "standard city permit fees." SUAA would then be free to use the South University area for its own promotions and events.
The records of the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair document the origins and development of the art fair from a small fair designed to promote business on South University avenue to one of the nation's premier, juried street art fairs. The documentation includes administrative records, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, posters, flyers and promotional material. The record group is divided into three series: Board and Committee Records, Other Materials, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Street Art Fair (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Fairs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor Art Fairs (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Art--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Artists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor Street Art Fair (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Art--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Artists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Art festivals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Fairs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Posters.; Slides.; Photographs.
- Board and Committee Records
  The Board and Committee series (1.1 linear feet) is made up of 5 subseries: Minutes, Financial, Bylaws and Board and Committee Members, Secretary's Notebook, and Chronological Files. Minutes appear throughout this series. The Minutes and the Chronological Files subseries are the two largest and contain some overlapping information.
  Also included in this series are the Bylaws ("Bylaws and Board and Committee Members") files and Financial files, as well as the Secretary's Notebook.
  - Minutes 1971-1999
    The Minutes subseries contains minutes and agendas from the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair board and committee meetings, as well as some other related materials such as board correspondence and announcements.
    - 1971-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - 1997 (Box 1)
    - 1998 (Box 1)
    - 1999 (Box 1)
  - Financial 1987-1995
    The Financial subseries consists mainly of budgets and expense reports for the art fair.
    - Audience Survey Results 1988 (Box 1)
    - Budgets 1987-1994 (Box 1)
    - Fair Expenses 1988-1995, 2 folders
      - 1988-1991 (Box 1)
      - 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws and Board and Committee Members 1976-1996
    - Mission Statement 1994 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws 1996, undated (Box 1)
    - Committee Members 1976-1982, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Articles of Incorporation 1975-1996 (Box 1)
  - Secretary's Notebook: minutes, correspondence, promotional materials, artist rosters 1976-1982, 2 folders
    (includes artists' evaluations of the 1976 fair)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1982 (Box 1)
  - Chronological Files 1968-1981, 2001
    The Chronological Files span from 1968 to February of 1981. These files include early committee meeting minutes unavailable elsewhere in the collection, correspondence, memoranda, artist rosters and evaluations of the fair by the artists, and some promotional materials. The earliest files, from 1968 to 1969, are arranged by topic, while the later files are arranged strictly chronologically.
    - 1968-1969, 4 folders
      - Committee Meetings and Correspondence April 1968-November 1969 (Box 1)
      - Artist Acceptance and Rejection Letters 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - Exhibitions, Activities, and Job Descriptions 1969 (Box 1)
      - Artist Rosters and Evaluations 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
      (includes a photo of a demonstrator and a poster for the third annual Flint Art Fair)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979-February 1981 (Box 2)
    - 2001 clippings collected by Bentley Historical Library archivist Kenneth Scheffel (Box 2)
- Other Materials
  The Other Materials series (0.4 linear feet) is made up of four subseries: Artists' Evaluations, the Mayor's Committee on Art Fairs, Press Releases, and Phil's Book. The Artists' Evaluations subseries covers 1986 to 1998. Also included in this subseries are annual sales reports and maps of the artists' booths. Some of the earlier artists' evaluations can be found within the Secretary's Notebook and the Chronological Files of the Board and Committee series.
  The Mayor's Committee on Art Fairs subseries contains the agendas and minutes of the meetings of the committee, from 1982 to 1990, as well as correspondence. The Mayor's Committee was formed in 1975. It was charged with setting "the rules and regulations for all the fairs to be held during Summer Bargain Days." Specific concerns initially had to do with establishing limits to the size of the ever-growing fairs and preventing "poachers" (unregistered peddlers) from encroaching on legitimate vendors' territory. The mayor chose representatives from City Hall, the University of Michigan, the Chamber of Commerce, the Downtown Businessmen's Association, the State Street Merchants' Association, the Free Fair, and the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair.
  Minutes from the meetings indicate that the committee dealt with financial and other administrative issues involved in running the three Ann Arbor art fairs, particularly those which overlapped with municipal concerns. City zoning, health regulations at the food stalls, and the use of the city's AATA bus system as a shuttle service are some of the issues addressed by the committee. The Chronological Files contain some of the earlier minutes of the Mayor's Committee on Art Fairs (which are not included in the Mayor's Committee on Art Fairs subseries), along with correspondence between the two committees.
  The Press Releases subseries covers 1985 to 1988. Although the series is divided into separate categories, such as "Press Kits," "Press Releases," and "Public Service Announcements," these files all contain similar types of announcements. This reflects the original arrangement of the materials.
  "Phil's Book" refers to the files of Phil Love, committee treasurer and construction crew leader in the mid-1980s. It is a log of some of the practical and logistical aspects of running the fair, such as booth setup and the supervision of workers and volunteers. Also included, in the "Daily Newsletter" folder, are the Daily Bulletins from 1985 through 1987. These bulletins were distributed to all of the participating artists and, along with the other contents of Phil's Book, provide a glimpse at many of the behind-the-scenes details necessary to ensure the smooth running of the fair.
  - Press Releases 1985-1991
    - Press Kits 1985-1986, 1988, 3 folders
      - 1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986 (Box 2)
      - 1988 (Box 2)
    - Press Releases 1987-1988, 2 folders
      - 1987 (Box 2)
      - Radio 1988 (Box 2)
    - Public Service Announcements 1986-1987, 2 folders
      - 1986 (Box 2)
      - 1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous: mailing lists, media lists, press kit lists, facts and figures, correspondence, announcements 1985-1991 (Box 2)
  - Mayor's Committee on Art Fairs 1982-1990
    - Meetings: agendas and minutes, 2 folders
      (some early meeting minutes can be found in the Chronological files of the Board and Committee series)
      - December 1982-October 1986 (Box 2)
      - February 1986-April 1990 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous circa 1980-1989 (Box 2)
  - Artists' Evaluations 1986-1998, 13 folders
    (includes annual sales reports and maps of fair booths)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
      (includes material from 1980)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
    - 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 2)
      (includes booth map for 1999)
  - Phil's Book 1985-1988
    (background on Phil Love's role in the fair can be found in the news release for November 13 in Press Kits, Press Releases, 1985, Other Materials)
    - Worker Recruitment June 1987 (Box 2)
    - Setup and Operation: "Visqueen; Garbage Cans/Crew; Standard Supplies, Week of Fair; Tuesday Set-Up; Saturday Night-Sunday Morning Close," July 1986 (Box 2)
    - Graceful Arch 1987 (Box 2)
    - Daily Newsletter 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous 1981-1987 (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Material series (1.3 linear feet) consists of two subseries: Scrapbooks, and Photographs and Slides. The Scrapbooks subseries is comprised of eight scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, photographs, publicity materials, and other miscellanea related to the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair. The scrapbooks cover the time period of 1960 through 1991. They were begun and kept by Street Art Fair founder Esther Rainville.
  The Photographs and Slides subseries is made up of four sub-subseries: Prints, Press Photos, Proof Sheets and Negatives, and Slides. Most of the photographs in the Prints sub-subseries are in black and white. The slides are all in color. Accompanying the slides for 1977 through 1981 is the file "Slide Script and Notes."
  - Photographs and Slides, circa 1960-1985
    - Prints
      - Art Fair 1980-1982, undated (Box 2)
      - Demonstrators undated (Box 2)
      - Press Kit Photos circa 1960-1985 (Box 2)
      - Other Prints 1985, Undated (Box 2)
        (color prints include corresponding negatives)
    - Press Photos
      - Photos Used in 1985 Press Kit (Box 2)
      - Possibilities for 1986 Press Kit (Box 2)
    - Proof Sheets and Negatives circa 1960-1980
      - Proof Sheets 1-36 (Box 2)
      - Negatives, Proof Sheets 37-48 (Box 2)
      - Large Negatives and Contact Sheets (Box 2)
    - Slides 1971-1985, 1996, undated, 1 folders; 5 volumes (Box 3)
      - Pre-1971 through 1976 (Box 3)
      - 1977-1981 Graceful Arch, South U Shot (banner), and others (Box 3)
      - Slide Script and Notes 1977-1981 (Box 3)
      - 1982-1985 (Box 3)
      - Slides of Event July 24-27, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks 1960-2005, 10 volumes
    (includes Street Art Fair posters and "Daily Bulletins")
    - 1960-1971 (Volume 1)
    - 1972-1976 (Volume 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Volume 3)
    - 1979-1981 (Volume 4)
    - 1973, 1982-1984 (Volume 5)
    - 1985-1986 (Volume 6)
    - 1987-1989 (Volume 7)
    - 1990-1991 (Volume 8)
    - 1989-1997 (Volume 9)
    - 1998-2005 (Volume 10)
Related Collections
Related material can be found in the Joyce Jones papers, also held by the Bentley Historical Library. Joyce Jones was the registrar of the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair for over fifteen years. Her collection includes minutes, annual reports, and program materials from the early 1960s through the late 1970s.